<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[SVIP | Blog]]></title>
  
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-30T21:27:34.936Z</updated>
  <id>http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SVIP]]></name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://zespia.tw/hexo/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Guest Blog: What Is The Key To Startup Success in the UK?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Guest-Blog-What-Is-The-Key-To-Startup-Success-in-the-UK/"/>
    <id>http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Guest-Blog-What-Is-The-Key-To-Startup-Success-in-the-UK/</id>
    <published>2014-11-29T21:09:37.000Z</published>
    <updated>2014-11-30T18:56:42.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With my graduation ceremony marking the end of one journey tomorrow, a new journey awaits me when I move to San Francisco this September. I feel very fortunate to be part of the inaugural class of the Silicon Valley Internship Programme. You can watch my 1-minute video intro <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O35tgpQD8bg" target="_blank" rel="external">here</a>.</p>
<p>I began preparing for the journey ahead of me by attending the <a href="http://www.pubsummit.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Pubsummit</a> event on July 8th, hosted by <a href="http://gigaom.com/2013/07/02/come-hang-out-with-gigaom-in-london-next-week/" target="_blank" rel="external">GigaOM</a>; I wasn’t sure what to expect, as this was the first networking event I have attended in a bar! It was a warm and sunny evening in the city so I was relieved to find upon arrival that the venue was shaded. Courtesy of the kind folks at <a href="https://twitter.com/geckoboard" target="_blank" rel="external">Gecoboard</a>, I was immediately given two free drinks vouchers. There was a welcoming buzz of conversation in the air and I couldn’t wait to get involved.</p>
<a id="more"></a>

<p><img src="/img/key1.jpg" alt=""></p>
<p>One of my goals for my year in the Silicon Valley is to pick up the skills necessary to run a successful startup when I return to the UK. To prepare for this, I decided to ask everyone I spoke with about what they thought was important for new startups and the startup community in the UK as a whole.</p>
<p>Having ordered a Tequila Lemonade, I put on my investigative hat and began taking part in some very interesting conversations.</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/xenophin" target="_blank" rel="external">Xen Lategan</a> from <a href="http://pxi.io/" target="_blank" rel="external">PXi Ventures</a> said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“You want the pressure of an investor. When you bootstrap, it may be safe but your velocity is also low.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/alokmatta" target="_blank" rel="external">Alok Matta</a> who has quit the corporate sphere in order to explore the startup world said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“There is lack of creativity in Europe. Instead of copying what has already been done and trying to solve problems that are not there, we need to focus on innovation.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/annadahlstrom" target="_blank" rel="external">Anna Dahlström</a>, a freelancing UX designer and founder of <a href="http://www.byflock.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">byflock</a> said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Know your priorities. It’s easy to get sidetracked.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="/img/key2.jpg" alt=""></p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/daniellevy1" target="_blank" rel="external">Daniel Levy</a>, the CEO of <a href="http://www.streetlike.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">StreetLike</a> said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Get mentors as soon as you can; find people who have done what you are trying to do.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Alec Dent, from <a href="http://www.blablacar.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">BlaBlaCar</a> said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“More people need to be willing to take the risk.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/Kat_Procopiou" target="_blank" rel="external">Katherine Procopiou</a>, from <a href="http://nexmo.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Nexmo</a> (a worth checking out SMS API) said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“People need to commit beyond the 9-5 and be passionate. For this to happen we need larger scale events to connect more people and higher profile speakers to inspire the community here.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/peterryder16" target="_blank" rel="external">Peter Ryder</a>, the co-founder of <a href="http://www.inkly.me/" target="_blank" rel="external">Inkly</a> said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Network, but don’t go looking for specific things; instead be open to opportunities. Go to events and just talk to different people. You don’t have to talk to everyone either. We got everything through networking!”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I really liked the informal and relaxed atmosphere throughout and was very impressed with the calibre of people in attendance. It is something I would definitely recommend to anyone in the startup world. I am looking forward to more events like this!</p>
<p>I’d like to give special thanks to Patti Silverman (SVIP Program Manager) who made me aware of this fun event and to <a href="https://twitter.com/hoshsadiq" target="_blank" rel="external">Hoshang Sadiq</a> my good friend and <a href="http://www.cs.kent.ac.uk/news/2013/ProjectFair/" target="_blank" rel="external">co-founder</a>, for helping me put together the material for this post.</p>
<p>What do you think is the key to startup success in the UK?</p>
<p><img src="/img/key3.jpg" alt=""></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>With my graduation ceremony marking the end of one journey tomorrow, a new journey awaits me when I move to San Francisco this September. I feel very fortunate to be part of the inaugural class of the Silicon Valley Internship Programme. You can watch my 1-minute video intro <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O35tgpQD8bg" target="_blank" rel="external">here</a>.</p>
<p>I began preparing for the journey ahead of me by attending the <a href="http://www.pubsummit.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Pubsummit</a> event on July 8th, hosted by <a href="http://gigaom.com/2013/07/02/come-hang-out-with-gigaom-in-london-next-week/" target="_blank" rel="external">GigaOM</a>; I wasn’t sure what to expect, as this was the first networking event I have attended in a bar! It was a warm and sunny evening in the city so I was relieved to find upon arrival that the venue was shaded. Courtesy of the kind folks at <a href="https://twitter.com/geckoboard" target="_blank" rel="external">Gecoboard</a>, I was immediately given two free drinks vouchers. There was a welcoming buzz of conversation in the air and I couldn’t wait to get involved.</p>
]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="startup, key, success, guest, UK" scheme="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/tags/startup-key-success-guest-UK/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Guest Blog: SVIP Class of 2013 lands in San Francisco]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Guest-Blog-SVIP-Class-of-2013-lands-in-San-Francisco/"/>
    <id>http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Guest-Blog-SVIP-Class-of-2013-lands-in-San-Francisco/</id>
    <published>2014-11-29T21:09:29.000Z</published>
    <updated>2014-11-30T18:56:42.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a long time coming for this year’s successful SVIP applicants. Spring and Summer were spent in interviews, match making with the startups, getting accepted (!), putting together visa paperwork, fedexing forms and queueing for the visa interviews. A process that was most aptly documented by Chris Atkin-Granville on his blog where he discusses <a href="http://california.chrisatk.in/blog/post/choosing-between-offers.html" target="_blank" rel="external">choosing offers</a> and the <a href="http://california.chrisatk.in/blog/post/visa-interviews.html" target="_blank" rel="external">visa interview</a>.</p>
<a id="more"></a>

<p><img src="/img/land1.jpg" alt="First night in Hacker House, Nick and Mario enjoying a hearty burrito."></p>
<p>Our flight departed from Heathrow airport. I had stayed in London overnight and enjoyed a late morning underground commute to the terminal. The Facebook thread read “Meeting area D”, and upon arriving I noticed someone who looked like Nick’s Facebook photo. The recognition of a kindred SVIPer sparked our conversation. Then there was Michael, trying to get his massive ski bag on the plane, ready to hit the slopes. Identifying him was more problematic, since his Facebook profile photo was that of Iron Man. Most of us we were meeting for the first time and it sure felt surreal.</p>
<p>A security gate here, a meal there and we were San Francisco bound. The 11 hour flight was spent watching in-flight movies, chatting and sleeping.</p>
<p>Upon our arrival a pre-booked shuttle took us to our new home. Most of the interns were staying together for the first month in a ‘hacker house’. OK, admittedly it’s a glorified hostel. But it is a pretty cool idea – throw a load of developers together in a relatively small space, usually people in the process of dreaming up their own start-ups and see what ideas breed among them. As with a lot of things appreciating our new residence was a matter of perception and <a href="http://paulwozniak.wordpress.com/2013/09/05/my-first-impressions-hacker-house/" target="_blank" rel="external">Paul had a good one</a>. A tasty burrito and a drink at the local later, everybody was tucked into their creeky beds. I don’t know about the others, but I couldn’t sleep with all the excitement pumping through my veins.</p>
<p>We awoke in the wee hours, helped ourselves to some breakfast courtesy of Vic the house owner and assembled at the LoopUp offices in Downtown San Francisco. LoopUp is one of the start-ups hosting three of the interns on the programme (Paul, Steward and Chris), whose co-CEO Mike Hughes also happens to be the founder of the SVIP and a great guy. So the LoopUp offices doubles up quite nicely as the SVIP HQ, with the added bonus of having a pool table and beer on tap. Once we’d gotten everyone over the painfully necessary admin hurdles, it was time for a little orientation. Lunch in a nice restaurant nearby and straight on to witness first hand what San Francisco entrepreneur Mark Dwight of Rickshaw bags had been busy with.</p>
<p>Over in Dogpatch area of San Francisco a bag manufacturer has taken residence in a big wooden hangar. Mark Dwight, who formerly worked in Silicon Valley’s tech sector decided to organize something more tangible. The company makes bags to order, in small batches by a crazy-efficient team. Mark ran us throught the materials, process and most importantly infected us with his enthusiasm for making a great product. For the lowdown on Rickshaw bags, check out <a href="http://bessey.io/blog/2013/08/31/inspiration/" target="_blank" rel="external">Matt’s blog post</a> and whilst you’re at it <a href="http://www.rickshawbags.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">make your own</a>.</p>
<p>The remainder the weekend was spent checking out the peer, getting to know one another over a sampling of local beers and hitting our local. On Sunday morning Mario Hayashi, Michael Howell and I were due to travel south to San Jose to start our internships with Nimble Storage. Michael Hughes kindly drove us to our hotel, but not before letting us sample some burgers from In-n-Out for the genuine Cali experience.</p>
<p>Needless to say I was stunned by the luxury of the hotel which Nimble Storage had arranged for us especially after my 5 years of student living. Thanks Nimble. I felt out of place, but mustered the courage to appreciate it whilst it lasted. Monday was our first day at work.</p>
<p>The first few days in SF were most memorable and were also set in ink by <a href="http://paulwozniak.wordpress.com/2013/08/30/dreams-for-the-year-ahead/" target="_blank" rel="external">Paul</a>, <a href="http://leewoodridge.wordpress.com/2013/09/08/the-move-and-the-first-week/" target="_blank" rel="external">Lee</a>, <a href="http://bessey.io/blog/2013/09/03/the-first-days/" target="_blank" rel="external">Matt</a>, <a href="http://taylore.net/?p=519" target="_blank" rel="external">Stewart</a>, <a href="http://california.chrisatk.in/blog/post/the-first-48-hours.html" target="_blank" rel="external">Chris A</a>, <a href="http://sqwiggle.me/san-francisco-baby/" target="_blank" rel="external">Chris H</a> and primarily pixels by <a href="http://pinotgrig.io/" target="_blank" rel="external">Barnaby</a> - check em out!</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>It’s been a long time coming for this year’s successful SVIP applicants. Spring and Summer were spent in interviews, match making with the startups, getting accepted (!), putting together visa paperwork, fedexing forms and queueing for the visa interviews. A process that was most aptly documented by Chris Atkin-Granville on his blog where he discusses <a href="http://california.chrisatk.in/blog/post/choosing-between-offers.html" target="_blank" rel="external">choosing offers</a> and the <a href="http://california.chrisatk.in/blog/post/visa-interviews.html" target="_blank" rel="external">visa interview</a>.</p>
]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="svip, class, 2013, new, flights, san francisco, internship" scheme="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/tags/svip-class-2013-new-flights-san-francisco-internship/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Life Outside the Start-Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Life-Outside-the-Start-Up/"/>
    <id>http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Life-Outside-the-Start-Up/</id>
    <published>2014-11-29T21:09:16.000Z</published>
    <updated>2014-11-30T18:56:42.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The SVIP is about much more than just day to day life working for a start-up. In fact, those who get the most out of the SVIP will be the one’s who take up all the other opportunities right there on their doorstep in Silicon Valley. Every day of the week there are breakfast meet ups where people get together to bounce around ideas, networking events hosted by yet another exciting new company with the chance to get to know who’s who. And we haven’t even mentioned the conferences yet. Doesn’t sound too interesting, a bit stuffy even? Wrong. You could learn almost anything you ever wanted to at one of the hundreds of conferences happening around the Bay Area, this is how people stay on top in a rapidly developing environment. And you almost always get a free goodie bag.</p>
<a id="more"></a>

<p>This weekend SVIP interns Paul Wozniak and Stewart Taylor took part in a hackathon hosted by <a href="http://hellahackoakland.splashthat.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Pandora</a>. “Make something cool with music” they said. “You have 32 hours. Go.”</p>
<p><img src="/img/life1.jpg" alt=""><br><img src="/img/life2.jpg" alt=""></p>
<p>We do have to give some credit to another SVIP intern, Mike Howell, here. Quote “Why would I want to spend all week programming for my start up, every evening working on my own project AND devote my weekend to staring at a computer screen?” Contrary to popular opinion, the SVIP does accept non super-geek candidates who like fresh air and daylight. Did we mention that there happens to be an Olympic class ski resort at Squaw Valley, just a few hours drive from San Francisco?</p>
<p>That said, Paul and Stewart did an awesome job representing the SVIP. Not only did they come up with working product that streams music based on your mood, they won. That means a free month of co-working space to launch it from, courtesy of <a href="http://www.portoffices.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Port Work Spaces</a>, and even more time to devote to getting square eyes. Watch this space.</p>
<p>You can also check out Paul’s blog about the experience <a href="http://paulwozniak.wordpress.com/2013/10/01/my-first-hackathon-hella-hack/" target="_blank" rel="external">here</a>.</p>
<p><img src="/img/life3.jpg" alt=""></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>The SVIP is about much more than just day to day life working for a start-up. In fact, those who get the most out of the SVIP will be the one’s who take up all the other opportunities right there on their doorstep in Silicon Valley. Every day of the week there are breakfast meet ups where people get together to bounce around ideas, networking events hosted by yet another exciting new company with the chance to get to know who’s who. And we haven’t even mentioned the conferences yet. Doesn’t sound too interesting, a bit stuffy even? Wrong. You could learn almost anything you ever wanted to at one of the hundreds of conferences happening around the Bay Area, this is how people stay on top in a rapidly developing environment. And you almost always get a free goodie bag.</p>
]]>
    
    </summary>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Guest Blog: Failcon]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Guest-Blog-Failcon/"/>
    <id>http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Guest-Blog-Failcon/</id>
    <published>2014-11-29T21:09:04.000Z</published>
    <updated>2014-11-30T18:56:42.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This Monday I went to my first conference. It was FailCon which is a conference where people from tech stand up in front of a room and talk about their failures. The idea stems from a core value in the valley, which is that failure is OK. Many people attribute the bay area’s success to this philosophy, as people are given a second chance, learn from their mistakes and are more likely to succeed in further endeavours.</p>
<a id="more"></a>

<p>There was a lot of content in the talks, and as it would be slightly overwhelming I’ll do some summaries of the talks I particularly enjoyed.</p>
<p>The first talk was given by Miki Johnson and Jackson Solway, a couple who started a company together. Their failure came when they noticed that they had two totally different hopes for the business they were creating. Startups can generally follow two routes: venture capital funding and organic growth. The first is “get big quick”, where your investors fund you, but push you hard for it; organic growth is as it sounds, the company grows within its means, using profit for growth. The problem was that one wanted the first option, and the other wanted the second. As two co-founders you can see how this caused a rift which wasn’t solvable with discussion. Miki has a fantastic blog post on the topic, and how to predict if this may happen to you, <a href="https://medium.com/what-i-learned-building/96540ba28355" target="_blank" rel="external">here</a>.</p>
<p><img src="/img/failcon1.jpg" alt="Why we fail"></p>
<p>Victor Lombardi presented a talk based on his book Why We Fail, in which he investigates the trends of failure in the tech industry. He covered a few examples of companies who seemed to have similar products, at similar times, with similar market shares, where one went on to become huge, and the other flopped; his question is why? He suggests that you can drop each of these failures into one of four groups:</p>
<ul>
<li>Perception</li>
<li>Audience</li>
<li>Competition</li>
<li>Technology</li>
</ul>
<p>One message which particularly hit me was “take your assumptions about your customers as a hypothesis and test them scientifically”. Never take something which you think “yeh, our customers definitely want that” as the truth. Take a survey, ask them what they think, and if the answer doesn’t come back how you expect then you’ve saved yourself a lot of time and effort.</p>
<p>Jon Crawford, a founder of Storenvy.com (<a href="http://joncrawford.com/post/20378314843/how-i-got-kicked-out-of-y-combinator-and-then-raised" target="_blank" rel="external">who was kicked out of YC</a>, but that’s another story) gave a talk which gave importance to something which I previously hadn’t thought much about: culture. He talked about the importance of having a set list of company mantras which every decision is made by, and having that list visible to new employees so that your company is aligned in its purpose. He made a very apt simile: employees effort is like vectors, if they are in different directions, their vector product sums to very little.</p>
<p><img src="/img/failcon2.jpg" alt="SVIP represent"></p>
<p>Gleb Budman of Backblaze wasted a million dollars on advertising. Gleb was told that he had a million dollars to spend on advertising, and it was his job to spend it wisely; this was big as his company had never had this much money to spend before, so they went off the wagon. <a href="http://blog.backblaze.com/2013/05/16/as-seen-on-ellen/" target="_blank" rel="external">This blog post</a> shows how they decided to target “moms” (they sell backup software…) by buying a prime slot ON the Ellen DeGeneres show and giving everyone in the audience an ipad mini with their software on. This stunt alone cost the company around $300,000 and they managed to waste almost all the rest targeting the same market. You might think this sounds awesome, except that mums weren’t interested! They were never going to buy it, no matter how much it was flaunted in front of them. The take away message is “find your niche and double down”.</p>
<p>In summary, I learnt a lot and think that I need to go to more conferences in the future as I feel like just being there improved my chances of ever being successful in my own startup.</p>
<p>Thanks to Paul Wozniak for the photos.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>This Monday I went to my first conference. It was FailCon which is a conference where people from tech stand up in front of a room and talk about their failures. The idea stems from a core value in the valley, which is that failure is OK. Many people attribute the bay area’s success to this philosophy, as people are given a second chance, learn from their mistakes and are more likely to succeed in further endeavours.</p>
]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="conference, first, failcon, failures, startups, learning" scheme="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/tags/conference-first-failcon-failures-startups-learning/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[LAUNCH Hack Hack Hack]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/LAUNCH-Hack-Hack-Hack/"/>
    <id>http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/LAUNCH-Hack-Hack-Hack/</id>
    <published>2014-11-29T21:08:54.000Z</published>
    <updated>2014-11-30T18:56:42.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This weekend I attended the <a href="http://hackathon.launch.co/" target="_blank" rel="external">Launch Hackathon</a>, right here in San Francisco. The event was billed as the largest of its type, with over 1000 hand-selected designers and developers competing for some great prizes, including a grand prize of $1.6k worth of investments and prize money. The event was MC’d by <a href="http://twitter.com/jason" target="_blank" rel="external">@Jason</a> (Jason Calacanis of Weblogs Inc., Mahalo, and more recently <a href="http://thisweekin.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">TWiST</a>), who did a splendid job of <a href="https://twitter.com/Jason/status/399365305706618880" target="_blank" rel="external">keeping things rolling</a>.</p>
<a id="more"></a>

<p><img src="/img/launch1.jpg" alt="LAUNCH"></p>
<p><strong>The Hack</strong><br>So myself and a couple of friends formed a team several months back, but despite many failed “brainstorming” meetups beforehand, pretty much turned up with no plan of what we wanted to make (great start).</p>
<p><img src="/img/launch2.jpg" alt="Left to right: Nick, Henry, Fred, Barney"></p>
<p>After throwing a few ideas around, and not really gaining any momentum, we settled (read forced) upon a product that aimed to simplify collation and organisation of online recipes.</p>
<p>The basic idea was to provide users with a Bookmarklet/Browser Extension that allowed them to add any recipe to a unified catalog or “playlist” which provided a simple overview with uniform formatting, measurement units, layout etc.</p>
<p>This idea quickly “pivoted” to simply shopping for recipes instead of ingredients. Instead of manually collating recipes, the app would allow users to search for meals and order required ingredients in a few clicks. The product would also allow users to shop efficiently by combining recipes with common ingredients (so you don’t end up with half a tin of tomatoes, for example).</p>
<p>With renewed focus (and a substantial amount of coffee), we came up with <a href="http://hackathon.launch.co/project/launch-hackathon-2013-svips-project" target="_blank" rel="external">“Quiche”</a> (formally Trolley):<br><img src="/img/launch3.jpg" alt="Quiche"></p>
<p>The app was built using <a href="http://import.io/" target="_blank" rel="external">Import.io</a>, <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/ec2/" target="_blank" rel="external">EC2</a>, <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/rds/" target="_blank" rel="external">RDS</a>, <a href="http://getbootstrap.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Bootstrap</a>, <a href="http://backbonejs.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">Backbone.js</a> and, again, a lot of caffeine products.<br>You can read more about what Quiche does <a href="http://hackathon.launch.co/project/launch-hackathon-2013-svips-project" target="_blank" rel="external">here</a>.</p>
<p><img src="/img/launch4.jpg" alt="Henry the Hacker"></p>
<p>Although the idea didn’t win any prizes (we could’ve helped ourselves by actually entering a few of the API competitions), we were awarded a respectable 85% from our two judges:<br>Judges scores<br>Judges’ scores</p>
<p><strong>TL;DR</strong><br>So, to summarise my feelings from LAUNCH:</p>
<ul>
<li>LAUNCH was by far the most well organised hackathon I’ve ever attended, everything just worked the way it should, there was clear attention to detail in all areas, and some great speakers to boot.</li>
<li><strong>Think bigger</strong>. In hindsight, I think I should’ve let me imagination run more when coming up with ideas, I was too quick to think “how can we implement that in two days”, which actually isn’t that important. If I were to repeat the process I would definitely want to go after a bigger problem.</li>
<li><strong>Sleep</strong>. Despite what people might say, I think getting solid sleep is critical to productivity, and, whilst it might be the done thing at hackathons, catching sub-three hours of sleep under a table is not going to yield the results you want.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>This weekend I attended the <a href="http://hackathon.launch.co/" target="_blank" rel="external">Launch Hackathon</a>, right here in San Francisco. The event was billed as the largest of its type, with over 1000 hand-selected designers and developers competing for some great prizes, including a grand prize of $1.6k worth of investments and prize money. The event was MC’d by <a href="http://twitter.com/jason" target="_blank" rel="external">@Jason</a> (Jason Calacanis of Weblogs Inc., Mahalo, and more recently <a href="http://thisweekin.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">TWiST</a>), who did a splendid job of <a href="https://twitter.com/Jason/status/399365305706618880" target="_blank" rel="external">keeping things rolling</a>.</p>
]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="launch, hackathon, innovation" scheme="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/tags/launch-hackathon-innovation/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Guest Blog: I, Car]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Guest-Blog-I-Car/"/>
    <id>http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Guest-Blog-I-Car/</id>
    <published>2014-11-29T21:08:45.000Z</published>
    <updated>2014-11-30T18:56:42.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The topic that’s got me – and it seems a great deal of others – hot under the collar lately is that of the ‘self driving’ car. As Google and others further the technology necessary for a world free from steering wheels, one can’t help but wonder just what that world will be like. Many have dabbled in this topic but I hope to raise some points here I’ve not myself heard.</p>
<a id="more"></a>

<p><strong>Resistance</strong><br>While we’ve come along way since the Y2K world, a time when people had a natural distrust for machines (seriously, it seems so ridiculous now, but I’m sure you can recall just as I do a time when adults held a genuine distrust for a computer). Now, finally, people have started having reasonable faith in glorified logic machines and are instead recognizing the people operating them are the ones increasingly often not to be trusted. As of late, the people most often in the spotlight of course are not drivers but rather the NSA. Still, the point stands; to quote a wonderful acronym coined in tech support circles, P.L.B.K.A.C: Problem Lies Between Keyboard And Chair. So surely if we take away the keyboard steering wheel, no one could take objection?</p>
<p>Fortunately, even if for whatever reason there is resistance to the concept, its not a topic we have to convince the world of all at once. As much as I wish I could say in a years time the roads will be filled (or indeed empty) with fully autonomous vehicles, the reality of this situation is we’re much more likely to get there via a few intermediary steps.</p>
<p>We’ll start, or rather we have started with computer assisted driving. Already cars are on the roads that can park themselves, emergency stop, warn you of a vehicle in your blind spot, and more features are added constantly. The next step of course is to switch roles; human assisted driving, systems akin to what Google is already testing on the streets. We’ll likely stay at this stage until the vast majority of things on the road are autonomous.</p>
<p>Eventually though, we’ll get to that wonderful point, where we can eliminate even the occasional need for a human at the helm. And that’s the time I’d like to focus on, when things get really interesting.</p>
<p><strong>Starting from scratch</strong><br>Once you’ve taken the driver out of the equation, the distinction between public and private transportation is bound to change. When a vehicle can drive itself, does it make sense for one individual or even household to own one? I certainly don’t think it does. It makes much more sense for the bare minimum number of vehicles needed to serve a populace to be in constant circulation than it does for your car to be parked outside your house waiting for you. This change will be much akin to how Toyota turned car manufacturing on its head with its Kanban process, moving an entire industry from stockpiling resources to instead maintaining the bare minimum of inventory needed for peak production, a system which they showed vastly improves efficiency.</p>
<p>Such a system brings several benefits. Firstly, fewer parked vehicles, one I have already touched on. In addition, we can expect more vehicle diversity; no longer is it necessary to take a stab at guessing what single vehicle will best suit your needs for the next 5+ years, and in doing so compromise on suiting any of them. Long gone will be the age of the 5 seater hatchback! Say hello instead to the all electric BatchelorPod, a single seater with an even smaller footprint than a Smart car. Once you tailor the vehicles on the road to accommodate precisely the number of people and baggage that want to be on the road, you reduce the total footprint hugely! This was recently and excellently demonstrated in a gif doing the rounds on tumblr:</p>
<p><img src="/img/tram.gif" alt="Cars vs tram"></p>
<p>And once that hurdle is cleared, once we relinquish ownership of an individual vehicle for the betterment of everyone in the system, we eliminate the car as a status symbol, gleefully crushing, in my mind at least, a ridiculous industry built around designing an object – who’s purpose is primarily functional – to instead best represent its owner.</p>
<p>That isn’t to say the automotive design industry is over. Far from it. Rather, their industry just received a tremendous breath of fresh air. Much of the design of a car once restricted by safety regulation is now gone! Windows? Seats that face forward? A dashboard? All these things are entirely irrelevant in this bold future. It seems to me car designers jobs are going to get a lot closer to Tony Stark’s; purpose building “suits” to transport or even entertain their precious cargo.</p>
<p><strong>The Three Laws of Robotics</strong><br>Isaac Asimov’s coined the three laws of robotics in his I, Robot series. While I’m sure he never intended for them to be taken as gospel outside of the world of science fiction, they are sensible and perhaps obvious laws that are bound to find their way into cars. Of particular interest in the context of autonomous vehicles is the first law:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A robot may not injure a human being or, through inaction, allow a human being to come to harm.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Substitute “robot” for “human” and I think you and I could both agree that the law should still stand, and by that logic one couldn’t have much issue with it. But I foresee an interesting predicament that given enough time is bound to present itself, that is, a situation in which an autonomous vehicle does not make the same decision that its driver would have, in order to harm fewer lives than a self preserving human would. It is in our nature to be self preserving, and it is entirely plausible that a situation could arise on the road where in order to prevent a larger fatal accident from occurring, a driver would need to sacrifice themself. An obvious example would be two children running into the road, or<br>catastrophic failure in a nearby much larger vehicle.</p>
<p>And this raises an interesting issue: If I am the passenger in that autonomous car, sealed in, blissfully unaware of my surroundings and the situation about to arise ahead… Is it acceptable for my life to be ended to save others? Are there certain circumstances when it is and isn’t? These are questions that as a society, we will have no choice but to come to a preemptive conclusion on, lest we leave it too late.</p>
<p><strong>Onwards and upwards</strong><br>That concludes my thoughts worth mentioning on the brave new world we are entering. I hope that, having finished somewhat ominously on the ethics of robotics, you don’t think I fear this future. Au contraire! I for one welcome our new steering wheel free overlords. I cannot wait to live in this mad and exciting future that will undoubtedly soon be reality.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>The topic that’s got me – and it seems a great deal of others – hot under the collar lately is that of the ‘self driving’ car. As Google and others further the technology necessary for a world free from steering wheels, one can’t help but wonder just what that world will be like. Many have dabbled in this topic but I hope to raise some points here I’ve not myself heard.</p>
]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="google, svip, self-driving car, automation, innovation" scheme="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/tags/google-svip-self-driving-car-automation-innovation/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Guest Blog: Mr Right-idea]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Guest-Blog-Mr-right-idea/"/>
    <id>http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Guest-Blog-Mr-right-idea/</id>
    <published>2014-11-29T21:08:36.000Z</published>
    <updated>2014-11-30T18:56:42.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the six months I have lived in San Francisco I have encountered a concentration of passionate people beyond anything I could have anticipated. The sheer number of start-ups that the city, and surrounding Bay Area, fosters can be attributed to a great number of factors and there are innumerable articles which try to address these. But it is this passion exhibited by the world renowned “founder” stereotype which has me fixated.</p>
<a id="more"></a>

<p>In my time here I’ve been to a number of “fire-side” chats, met more founders than any normal city could even contain, and had more conversations than I care to even try and count with friends about potential projects. Some of these occasions have even been interesting and/or informative. But the one nagging question that I always find myself asking is why did you choose this idea? How do you know when to just go for it and commit to something? I’m yet to receive a solid answer that really satisfies.</p>
<p>Like most developers, I always have a side project. If not multiple side projects. In fact since I’ve started recording my ideas and side projects, I can tell you that I have over one hundred. And not a single one even near completion. I could blame this on all sorts of things, like the fact that I get very excited by starting a project, or conversely that I’m too lazy to put in the time beyond that point and finish them. Forgetting the honeymoon period arguments, I am yet to find myself bursting with that pure enthusiasm and passion for an idea of my own that I’ve seen in so many other people.</p>
<p>I’ll be honest, this has at times made me feel a little bit jealous. I am envious of the fact that so many people around me have fallen in love with one of their own ideas and are pursuing something that they believe in. But what grates on me most is when that idea, which is of course going to change the world, is just yet another niche social network; yet another unwanted consumer app; yet another wearable big data augmented reality digital dispatch service that’s going to disrupt… pretty much nothing.</p>
<p>All of my British cynicism aside, I think I’ve had some pretty good ideas, some which definitely had more potential than fully funded companies I’ve encountered. So why didn’t I experience that same passion? Why wasn’t I burning with the desire to take that idea and force it into fruition? To see it succeed beyond anything I initially imaged? To believe in it with enough zeal to make it contagious?</p>
<p>After thinking long and hard a few potential reasons or causes have become apparent to me. None of them definitive, and all unlikely to be the sole motive, but strangely they all glisten with parallels to the world of dating and relationships. Let’s check out the options:</p>
<p><strong>Higher standards</strong><br>Simply enough, other people are willing to settle for second best, or worse. A reluctance could be due to an over-inflated ego, or an inability to see the beauty inside, but I’m not sure how much effect being shallow or elitist could have on ones ideas.</p>
<p><strong>Waiting for “The One”</strong><br>The billion dollar idea, that elusive golden ticket, Mr Right. Whatever it’s called, I do feel like I’m waiting for that concept I’d be willing to marry and settle down with. But do some people just get lucky early on, or does this boil down to the previous point of having higher or lower standards?</p>
<p><strong>First love infatuation</strong><br>Do people just fall in love with the first serious idea they have, and then fail to see the greener grass beyond their bubble happily ever after? Maybe, but we all know there are plenty more fish in the sea and any founder or investor who’s done their market research should be able to see this for most ideas. Unless of course you have found a golden ticket, committing to the first cool idea that comes to your head may seem reckless.</p>
<p><strong>Afraid of being hurt</strong><br>The core concept of the Silicon Valley Internship Programme is teaching the British that it is OK to fail. It does seem possible that an openness to failure would make one more willing to take the leap of faith. But even with the knowledge that it’s better to have loved and lost than to never have loved at all, we’re still no better off knowing when to love. Unless of course you just take the first path you stumble across.</p>
<p><strong>Lack of self belief</strong><br>I don’t think anyone would ever accuse me of this, in fact they’re much more likely to call me a narcissist, but it does seem logical that if one were not to believe in oneself then one might be less inclined to pursue ones ideas.</p>
<p><strong>Because you don’t really want it</strong><br>Almost the opposite of the fear of failure or getting hurt is the possibility of being perfectly content with being perpetually in pursuit. The start-up life is always shown to be very glamorous, young and exciting, so why not tap some of that but without any of the stress and bother of actually starting up? After all, it’s not the kill, it’s the thrill of the chase.</p>
<p>These all seem like very good reasons or even excuses not to fall in love with an idea and experience the passion, and I’m sure they’re pleasing to cynics and pessimists. Even worse is the fact that the only conclusions that can be drawn from this are the cliches already in use on the other side of our analogy; “keep trying”, “don’t give up”, “don’t look too hard”, “it’ll happen eventually”. I guess I’ll just keep creating, waiting for Mr Right-Idea to come along, and hope the passion finds me eventually. And even if I become the old cat lady of entrepreneurs, I still want to hear the stories from the people out there right now with that passion, and the reasons why they seized an idea and decided to go for it.<br>Are you a founder? Have you turned an idea into success or failure? Share the reasons behind your decision to take that leap of faith with @barneyjackson and @SVIPUK to be part of the discussion.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>In the six months I have lived in San Francisco I have encountered a concentration of passionate people beyond anything I could have anticipated. The sheer number of start-ups that the city, and surrounding Bay Area, fosters can be attributed to a great number of factors and there are innumerable articles which try to address these. But it is this passion exhibited by the world renowned “founder” stereotype which has me fixated.</p>
]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="founder, svip, right idea, stereotype, risks" scheme="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/tags/founder-svip-right-idea-stereotype-risks/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Guest blog: First SVIP hackathon]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Guest-blog-First-SVIP-hackathon/"/>
    <id>http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Guest-blog-First-SVIP-hackathon/</id>
    <published>2014-11-29T21:08:23.000Z</published>
    <updated>2014-11-30T18:56:42.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend we held our very first SVIP hackathon. It was a surprisingly unrushed and pleasant affair much different to what I’d experienced before during game jams. Personally I think that it was the familiarity and homeliness of the LoopUp offices that did it. Stewart, Paul, Naomi, Ben, Mario, Michael, Chris A, Chris H all attended to work on their ideas.</p>
<a id="more"></a>

<p><img src="/img/firsthack1.jpg" alt="Mike (middle) impressing all with his implementation of The Matrix."></p>
<p>Mario, Mike and I drove up along the now familiar 101 from San Jose into San Francisco that rainy evening to greet everyone else. Having worked on a project together for Angel Hack we decided to try our luck at individual projects. In light of upcoming St Valentine’s day, I opted to appify an earlier program which could produce musical countdowns. The concept is simple: create a countdown via mobile-web interface where for each day the giftee can see a new song, picture and quote of your choosing but only once.</p>
<p>I drafted my UX design many times on paper that evening, starting with 9 screens and ending with just 4. Saturday and Sunday morning were spent implementing.</p>
<p>For a simple app like this, paper prototyping really worked because I could iterate quickly and have a clean implementation plan. Once a design was ready I could imagine what it would be like to use the app and modify anything that didn’t work.</p>
<p>For the implementation I used Bootstrap, Backbone.js, Parse.com since I’d been learning them already. Despite having a design I still ended up spending most of my time adjusting the UI. I recall feeling that in comparison to the ideas of the others mine seemed insignificant, but at some point I tuned out the doubts with some music and got coding.</p>
<p>Other ideas that were developed that weekend included a web-based job applications software, collaborative software lib, distributed system for doing cheeky things with BitCoins, email revolutionizer and an app that was aimed at improving company communication. All worthy challenges which address real-world problems.</p>
<p>Between coding we played ping-pong (Chris and Paul being ridiculously good since they work at LoopUp and play every day), had coffee, did Subway runs for breakfast, lunch and dinner and had a couple of beers. After 6 months people had gelled together well and there was a definite sense of camaraderie.</p>
<p>Both nights I’d spent sleeping comfortably on the floor listening to the rain ceaselessly overflowing the gutters. It reminded me of the UK.</p>
<p><img src="/img/firsthack2.jpg" alt="Naomi and Paul taking a well-deserved break from revolutionizing email"></p>
<p>Sunday was the day of “judging” with three startup old-hands attending. I quote “judging” as it was more like a brainstorming session discussing the potentials of each idea, downsides, areas to focus and danger zones. The main purpose of which was of course to nudge us into action and actually starting a company. Several of us have already started working on startup ideas, which is reassuring – all it takes is to choose a direction and start walking.</p>
<p><strong>Takeaways:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Paper prototype – quick, easy, saves time in the long run</li>
<li>Get your head down – even if others don’t get your idea, get it done, make a prototype, I’ve found that a working program was far more convincing, it’s the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stone_Soup" target="_blank" rel="external">old stone soup principle</a></li>
<li>Choose a big problem – don’t be afraid of addressing something tough, it will naturally stimulate conversation from others</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>Last weekend we held our very first SVIP hackathon. It was a surprisingly unrushed and pleasant affair much different to what I’d experienced before during game jams. Personally I think that it was the familiarity and homeliness of the LoopUp offices that did it. Stewart, Paul, Naomi, Ben, Mario, Michael, Chris A, Chris H all attended to work on their ideas.</p>
]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="first, hackathon, matrix, svip, 2013" scheme="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/tags/first-hackathon-matrix-svip-2013/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Welcome Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Welcome-Blog/"/>
    <id>http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/11/29/Welcome-Blog/</id>
    <published>2014-11-29T21:07:07.000Z</published>
    <updated>2014-11-30T18:56:42.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>“Propose to an Englishman any principle, or any instrument, however admirable, and you will observe that the whole effort of the English mind is directed to find a difficulty, a defect, or an impossibility in it. If you speak to him of a machine for peeling a potato, he will pronounce it impossible: if you peel a potato with it before his eyes, he will declare it useless, because it will not slice a pineapple. Impart the same principle or show the same machine to an American or to one of our Colonists, and you will observe that the whole effort of his mind is to find some new application of the principle, some new use for the instrument.” – Charles Babbage</p>
</blockquote>
<a id="more"></a>

<p>As I sat down to write this post, I felt a warm glow of pride knowing that the computer, the ARM architecture on my machine’s chipset and the World Wide Web – over which I’m now sharing this stream of consciousness – are all British inventions.  Then, reality snapped me out of my patriotic reverie as I noticed the ‘HP’ logo on my laptop, running Microsoft’s OS on an Intel chipset, powering a Mozilla browser to access a Google Document.</p>
<p>Underpinned by an excellent university network, Britain continues to be one of the great innovating countries of the world.  Yet, for all the innovations originating from Britain’s Boffins, the ability to commercialize these innovations and build new business models remains embarrassingly elusive.</p>
<p>I have lived in San Francisco since coming to the US 17 years ago to attend business school.  About 10 years ago, I started a company <a href="http://www.loopup.com" target="_blank" rel="external">(www.LoopUp.com)</a> with a friend of mine, Steve ‘Mr Buckethead’ Flavell, whom I met at Stanford.  Unconventionally, we decide to start our company simultaneously in London and San Francisco and we have since grown to a team of 85 people spread among offices in London, San Francisco, Boston and Hong Kong.</p>
<p>Every few years I join with fellow Brit entrepreneurs in the Bay Area to take part in meetings set up by the UK government.  These well-intentioned discussions aim to understand ‘Why Silicon Valley Works’ and to tease out some magic formula that can be replicated back in Britain to reinvigorate the tech sector.  Studying a unique ‘cluster’ such as the one that exists in Silicon Valley does indeed reveal a fascinating interplay between companies, financiers, Universities, human capital, local demand conditions and the government.  However, no matter how intriguing it may be to analyse this interplay of elements, the output is essentially descriptive.  It’s helpful in understanding how Silicon Valley works, but it yields little information telling us how to actually go and build a similar cluster.</p>
<p>Something that always strikes me when I speak with entrepreneurs who have gravitated towards Silicon Valley is how important ‘just being here’ seems to be to their aspirations.  Digging a little deeper, you find that the underlying feeling of the Valley is that anything is possible, and if others can succeed, why can’t I?  The heady mix of effort, luck and hope (along with a pinch of inspiration) is the attitudinal magic that powers the interplay between the actors and provides the engine of entrepreneurship.  To make a somewhat contentious generalisation, the natural British response to the new is to analyse and criticize.  This feeds perfectly into the sense of humour, but curtails the wide-eyed enthusiasm that gets businesses started.  The dirty secret of entrepreneurship is that it is a portfolio game: you need lots of people trying lots of different things and one of them, whether by luck or judgement, will succeed.  If success has a healthy mix of luck to go with the judgement, then an enthusiastic community (which sees failure as good experience for the next attempt) will always outperform a community where analytical criticism rules and fewer, though better-conceived, attempts are made.  Natural selection is a powerful force in entrepreneurship!</p>
<p>Given this world view, the question remains, ‘What can be done to help the UK’s tech sector?’  The answer is easy: try some things and see what works.  So, let’s try something!</p>
<p>Entrepreneurs in Silicon Valley have found that attitude is one of the biggest benefits of being here and this attitude makes them realize that all those successful entrepreneurs are not so different from you and me.  They also understand that the biggest and most important thing about starting a company is simply starting, even if you don’t have the perfect idea (and it will change anyway once you begin).  How do we instill this attitude into the brightest of the next generation of British talent?</p>
<p>Enter the Silicon Valley Internship Programme.  We take newly minted software engineering grads from the UK and pair them up with hot start-ups for a one year ‘internship’.  What better way to help people understand what’s going on here than to bring them over to work in the environment and be part of the early evolution of a tech company?  We have been able to quickly pull together what we need to make it happen with some tremendous help from the SV start-up community, the British Consulate and so many kind people who’ve gone out of their way to help.</p>
<p>As if to prove my point about this contrast in attitudes, I floated the idea of taking on some UK grads to the start-up community associated with Stanford and had an overwhelmingly positive response with enthusiastic offers of help.  I posted the same thing on a UK Facebook community page and received a two-page response from a Brit explaining why it will never work.</p>
<p>Do you want to prove that guy wrong?  Are you ready to jump in, learn from the best and bring the Silicon Valley attitude to the UK?  Then join us!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Twenty years from now, you will be more disappointed by the things that you didn’t do than by the ones you did do.  So throw off the bowlines.  Sail away from the safe harbor.  Catch the trade winds in your sails.  Explore.  Dream.  Discover.”  Mark Twain</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>“Propose to an Englishman any principle, or any instrument, however admirable, and you will observe that the whole effort of the English mind is directed to find a difficulty, a defect, or an impossibility in it. If you speak to him of a machine for peeling a potato, he will pronounce it impossible: if you peel a potato with it before his eyes, he will declare it useless, because it will not slice a pineapple. Impart the same principle or show the same machine to an American or to one of our Colonists, and you will observe that the whole effort of his mind is to find some new application of the principle, some new use for the instrument.” – Charles Babbage</p>
</blockquote>
]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="welcome, blog, svip, programme, entrepreneur" scheme="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/tags/welcome-blog-svip-programme-entrepreneur/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[SVIP 2014 Postmortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/10/15/Guest-blog-SVIP-2014-postmortem/"/>
    <id>http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/2014/10/15/Guest-blog-SVIP-2014-postmortem/</id>
    <published>2014-10-16T03:18:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2014-11-30T18:56:42.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well it’s been a whole year. A whole year and I can hardly believe it. Still time waits for no man and myself and the rest of the SVIP Class of 2014 are soon to move on to greener pastures, exciting new projects and adventures.</p>
<a id="more"></a>

<p>I asked a few of my fellow SVIPers to sum up their time with the SVIP. Barnaby reflects – “I feel this year has given me an informed insight and opinion on this profession, the sector and Silicon Valley. It has put a lot into perspective for me, as well as obviously learning a great deal. The biggest thing I think though is that it has helped me start to form an idea of what I want to be doing in the future.” Chris and Nick whole-heartedly agree, saying more people should apply. And I think it’s clear from any one of our faces that we’re all taking away something money can’t buy from this experience.</p>
<p>Over the course of the year, many startup ideas floated around amongst the SVIPers. Some disappeared into thin air, some took shape and a few made it into the hands of their first users. Of particular note is the project to build a SaaS web-store plugin. Its creator (who prefers to stay anonymous) succeeded in getting funding to further develop his idea but chose to do so whilst working full-time. “The money offered by some of the startups is just too tempting” he says, and it’s true for the rest of us. Stewart too has decided to combine full-time work and further development of “Cruity” a custom recruitment platform used by the SVIP to power its own application process and a worthy competitor to Resumator.</p>
<p>But what are the things that we would do differently, given the chance? In my peers’ words:</p>
<ul>
<li>Be more focused</li>
<li>Carve out time at the weekends towards hacking</li>
<li>Attend more startup events</li>
<li>Spend more time with my mentor</li>
<li>Finish the side projects</li>
</ul>
<p>Although these may sound specific to startups and software engineering, they’re really not that different from what many aspiring young people go through during this time of their lives. It’s about searching for meaningful work, that speaks to our purpose, removing unnecessary distractions and fully actualizing that initial flood of inspiration. Looking at the list above, a nagging question enters my mind, “have I done enough this year?”.</p>
<p>Recently we’ve all been tuning in to a Stanford lecture series on “How to start a startup”, where Sam Altman pointed out that one of the biggest regrets of company founders is choosing an idea which didn’t quite resonate with them. And for this resonance to occur, queue cliche, the founders must “know themselves”.</p>
<p>Throughout the year I’ve heard some great advice from company founders. Amongst them was the surprisingly simple and reassuring words from Nimble Storage’s Varun and Umesh:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Find the industry which you want to innovate in, work in a good company within this industry, succeed and don’t be afraid to quit when the right idea comes knocking on the door.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What this says to me is that there’s no need to rush into a startup which you don’t feel passionate about, but you can build up to it by working on projects which really interest you with people you really like. And it gives me great clarity to see this opinion seconded in “Before the Startup” by Paul Graham. It’s the simple “do what you want” rule of thumb which feels so true, one that I hear over and over and over.</p>
<p>Undoubtedly, this year in Silicon Valley has been a journey of personal growth for us all. So perhaps the greatest thing about the SVIP, is that it has given us a chance to experiment, experience and learn by working in the environment in which we want to innovate in. Through a myriad events, founder meetups, hackathons, parties, road trips we’ve all weathered and reflected on our own powers and what we can achieve with them, and hopefully gained a better appreciation for the people who make our lives worthwhile.</p>
<p>Special thanks to Mike Hughes for reaching out and Naomi Coe for herding the cats, we hope to one day return the favor.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>Well it’s been a whole year. A whole year and I can hardly believe it. Still time waits for no man and myself and the rest of the SVIP Class of 2014 are soon to move on to greener pastures, exciting new projects and adventures.</p>
]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="postmortem, SVIP, end of an era, 2013, 2014" scheme="http://blog.siliconvalleyinternshipprogram.com/tags/postmortem-SVIP-end-of-an-era-2013-2014/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
